this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
sea radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host johannesproni and today
we'll be discussing behavioral code
analysis with Adam Thornhill Adam is a
programmer who combines degrees in
engineering and psychology he is the
founder of code scene where he designs
code analysis tools to that Empower
teams to build great software he's the
whole tour of several books software
design x-rays fixed technical adapt to
it behavioral code analysis the
best-selling your code as a crime scene
list for the web and patents in C he is
also a public speaker so welcome Adam
and is there anything a miss that you'd
like to add so thank you very much for
that introduction no I think that pretty
much sums it up I've been working with
soft development for 25 years and I
still enjoy it very much good so well
let's start then with the first question
which will be basically definition so
can you tell us what is behavioral code
analysis sure so Behavior code analysis
is steady that you approach code
analysis from the people side so in a
behavior code I'm courses the code
itself is an important piece but it's
even more important to understand how
the organization and developers behind
the code have worked to create it that's
where the true information is
okay can you tell us what kind of
problems does it help to solve maybe
giving also some examples from real
projects so just people can understand a
bit what use they can make of it yeah
definitely so there are a number of
additional information points that the
behavior code analysis adds so if you
look at just the code itself for static
snapshot of the code we will never be
able to understand the Dynamics of what
actually happens when you build a system
and that simply means that we won't be
able to differentiate technical depth
with a low interest rate technical depth
that's in stable code versus technical
depth that's in code that's much more
volatile and actually affects the
organization another big advantage of
Behavioral code analysis is that since
we take these people perspective
perspective on code we are also able to
do a lot of interesting organizational
and social analysis okay can you give us
maybe a small example the two some
problem you helped an organization
address with this just a short one if
you've got one yeah there are a couple
of interesting problems that behavioral
code analysis can help with I like to
think that one of the most important use
cases for Behavioral code analysis is to
not only identify but also prioritize
technical depth the reason you need a
behavioral code analysis is because
technical depth I mean the tragedy
behind it is that there's so much of it
out there and you pick up a code base at
random and it will have tons of
application code depth most
organizations simply cannot fix all of
that depth at once you need to use your
time wisely and by running a behavioral
code analysis called a hotspot analysis
you can basically identify which
technical depth represents the largest
risk whereas most of our waste occurring
and what parts of the code become bulmax
for their development teams and the way
you do this is basically by looking at
the behavioral pattern of which parts of
the code that we work with as developers
now often do we work with that parts of
the code so by then find those patterns
we can identify hot spots and hotspots
are simply complicated code that we have
to work with often and some great
candidates but starting to pay down
technical debt okay so if I'm listening
correctly here you are saying well as we
know lots of organizations have lots of
technical adapt in that systems but
behavioral code analysis will help us
prioritize where to work on and avoid to
address technical depths in parts of the
code that actually are not going to
change much and so addressing that
particular technical that would be
expensive but not necessarily a good
idea am I understanding correctly
exactly that's a pretty accurate summary
the reason why this is important to
prioritize this because I mean if you
pick up your average Enterprise code
base you could probably spend two three
years just refactoring and paying down
technical debt and if you would do that
I mean you wouldn't be able to add a
single feature you would basically be
out of business you would be Netscape
right and you really don't want that if
you have technical debt or low quality
code and it's in stable parts of the
code code that hasn't been changed in
months even years then that's technical
depth that you need to be aware of
because it could very well be a
long-term risk but it's probably not
urgent right now
so what the behavior code analysis lets
you do is to identify the parts of the
code where you spend most of your time
by focusing your refactories those parts
of the code you're more or less
guaranteed that your work has a real
impact a positive influence and moving
forward okay that's great now all this
is good but can you tell us in practice
the core idea I know where does the data
come from where do you get the
information to the to do this analysis
what kind of tools you get information
from yeah I should have covered that
because that's of course core to get
this going so with the behavior code
analysis we obviously need behavioral
data of how we as developers have been
directed with the code we're building
and this sounds like uh some kind of uh
survival some kind of scary thing but
it's not because all organizations
already have all the data they need what
I'm talking about is Version Control
Systems like git because git history I'm
so fascinated by Version Control because
I think that historically we have used
Version Control like it more or less as
an overly complicated backup system and
then occasionally as a collaboration
tool but when doing so we have also
built up this absolutely wonderful data
source over how the system evolved which
developers that worked in which part how
often we worked there and what happened
to the code when we did so so Behavior
code analysis is about analyzing Version
Control history that's the most
important piece of information the code
itself of course because we need to
differentiate good from bad and a third
data source that I've been using more
and more over the past years is product
management tools like jira and Azure
devops okay so you basically do some
kind of cross check analysis from the
source code itself and the repository as
well as the tools the project management
or product management tools I guess you
can do with this tell me if I'm guessing
correctly you can also do tracking like
of bugs where bugs are in the code and
this kind of things in the analysis is
that correct by using these tools like
Jada exactly that's absolutely right
when I started up with a behavior code
analysis I was mostly relying on Virtual
control and code but what very often
happens is that you more or less need to
make the business case for larger
improvements to the technical leaders to
the management they might be people that
are not that familiar to look at source
code right so that's where I start to
use more and more product management
data because it can help you connect the
dots so not only can you show that okay
we have this complicated piece of code
where we spend most of our time working
you can also make it relevant to the
business by showing that look we
actually had 20 defects in this code
just over the past six months and the
nice thing with that is that then you
can also visualize the return on
investment if you pay down that
technical debt so the expectation would
be that if that part of the code is made
more clear and easier to understand they
would also significantly reduce the
number of defects so this would be a
very real win that you could show and
celebrate okay that's good basically
it's also a good to well say a good way
doing behavioral code analysis to
actually connect the technical needs
with the business needs as well I guess
so in terms of you want to address
technical debt in a part of the code the
code base and you can actually
justify those actions from a business
perspective as well exactly and I think
that's super important not only now but
also moving forward for many
organizations because if you look at the
research that has been done over let's
say the past five years we have actually
learned a lot about technical labs and
how it impacts organizations and if you
looked at research you will see it's a
pretty depressing read Because what it
shows is basically that average
organization wastes somewhere between 23
to up to 42 percent of developers time
dealing with tactical depth and bad code
the reason this happens is simply
because code itself lacks visibility
it's a very abstract thing so even if
you as a potential business manager
knows that okay this is the waste that
happens in the industry on average it's
very hard to relate that to your
situation to your code base so I like to
think that adding this Behavior I died
on top of it then this small business
oriented data can really really help you
understand okay what's our situation
what's our level of technical depth what
are consequences of it and by doing so
and by being able to visualize code at
the business level we can finally make
sure that everyone involved not only we
as developers but also product people
and managers have the shared situational
awareness and I think that's critical to
tackle a large problem like technical
adapt okay and now a question that might
sound a bit simplistic to you but I
think will help our listeners a bit so
most developers have probably used
static code analysis in their tools but
these tools that tell you you've got 52
years of technical Deb the call Quality
is so and so cyclomatic complexity in
some files but
I guess not everybody has heard about
behavioral code analysis just yet so
what are the differences between the two
how is behavioral code analysis
different from static code analysis
that's a great question so let me try to
clarify that the reason I start to work
with behavior code analysis was where we
match your reaction to static analysis
and don't get me wrong on this I do
think that static analysis definitely
has its place static analysis is a
really really good feedback loop when
writing code however what static
analysis is not good at is to prioritize
technical adapt or prioritizations and
the reason I say this is because with
static analysis what you can do very
easily with these tools is that you can
identify bad code static analysis is
really good at that but what static
analysis can never tell you is the
impact of that bad code is it technical
depth is it waste there's no way to tell
right and that's why you end up with
these long long list of like 5000
critical issues with too much
information it's simply it's simply no
longer actionable so the main advantage
of a behavior code analysis is that yeah
it can also identify bad code but as
opposed to static analysis you do get
the priorities based on how you actually
work with the code the second big big
difference is that static analysis is
limited to the code itself and one of
the great tragedies of software design
is that organization that builds the
code is invisible in the code itself and
with the behavior account analysis you
can shine a light on that whole
dimension right so Behavior code
analysis also lets you look into the
people side of things you can see how
the different teams are organized how
they work with the code and that makes
it possible to evaluate things like
architectural fit which is really really
interesting okay that's quite
interesting so it sounds like they are
actually
somehow related but actually a more
complementary behavioral code analysis
goes more in depth into some properties
of the code base and the system itself
as I understand it is not correct yeah I
mean I'm obviously biased but I do like
to think that behavior code analysis
gives a more holistic picture of
software development I think that's
really important because getting the
people side of software wrong has
probably killed more projects than even
Visual Basic right so it's really really
important to understand that Dimension
too so now let's go a bit more in detail
to understand better the behavioral code
analysis aspect so we talk about
organizational information in various
dimensions of around people and the code
but what kind of information may be
about a bit more detail on the
information that can be inferred from
the behavioral code analysis what kind
of properties of the code base I don't
know can we in fire architectural
properties for example or just the code
can we infer I don't know the fitness of
for purpose of the team structure or not
can it help also with these aspects I
mean can you give us a bit more detail
on the kind of information that we
concretely can find sure I'd be happy to
walk you through a couple of stories
that I've seen happen in the world that
would be great yeah you can do a lot of
different things so Behavior Q analysis
is not one thing it's a lot of different
techniques you won't use all of them at
once right it depends a little bit on
your context and the problem you're
trying to solve a couple of years ago to
give you one example on what you can do
I worked with with an organization that
had a pretty large system couple of
million lines of code had a significant
development organization I think 50 60
developers they had used component-based
architecture for a long long time and
that architecture had served them well
and consequently they also had component
based teams so that each team had
ownership of our particular component
and the advantage with that
organizational setup is obviously that
you have a very clear ownership in a
clear area of responsibility the
drawback is that you get ridiculously
long lead times because if you have a
feature that kind of crosses over
architectural boundaries then you need
to coordinate between multiple teams so
what they did was that they decided to
Let's shift around and let's do feature
teams so I simply took their existing
organization and split them up into I
think six or seven different feature
teams and let them loose on the code
base and of course what happened now was
that everything simply slowed down there
were tons of merge conflicts the lead
times got even worse and no one was
really happy with this situation and
that's so typical of this type of
organizational issues that you kind of
see the symptoms but the root causes are
where we were hard to communicate so
what we did was that we used Behavior
code analysis to Simply analyze and
visualize what does the code looks like
what are the different areas and where
in the code are the different teams
working and what you could very clearly
show was that basically every single
component became a gigantic coordination
ball Max because it had continuous
contributions from five or even six
different teams and that helps you kind
of understand that okay we do have a
mismatch between the way we are
organized and what our architecture
chords does that make sense to you yes
and how did you solve that one because
you said it component based kind of
system and organization they invent two
feature teams and then did you find a
third way to actually different way to
organize the teams the thing is that
very often what you need to do is you do
need to reorganize the teams or
reorganizing their teams alone without
also costing an eye on the architecture
will never ever work right so the proper
solution in this case was to kind of
just roll back get back to the component
teams because yes there were a ton of
drawbacks but at least that drawbacks
were well understood right from there
you simply had to avoid the architecture
to support feature teams so instead of
having these technical responsibilities
where every single component represented
a technical section they move towards a
more feature-oriented architecture so
that you could have more isolated pieces
where each team could work with larger
autonomy without having to step on the
toast of another team and force painful
coordination meetings so it's always
teams and architecture always go hand in
hand it's actually quite a great and
important point because I've seen
organizations that do this kind of
organization let's go because feature
teams are the way to go let's do that
and have those sorts of problems but
they never are never able to kind of
roll back or even justify what they are
trying to achieve here are the things
that using behavioral code analysis say
well we try this actually look at what
is happening in the behavior in the code
is a bad idea so with the current
architecture the best we can do is still
component teams and so if Anderson
correctly what they say well this is the
best we can do at the moment if you want
to go to feature themes you have to
refactor the architecture of the system
as well and basically the behavioral
code analysis tools we are telling you
this am I correct yeah that's pretty
accurate the nice thing is that once you
decide to re-architecture architecture
then you can actually get a bit of
support from behavioral code analysis as
well because there is this other
analysis called the change coupling
which is again something that you cannot
see in the code itself because change
coupling is about things that tend to
change at the same time and that sounds
really really vague but what I mean by
that is simply that could be a CCS when
you make a commit you always modify two
different files as part of the same
commit simple one could be the client
that the other one could be the server
for example so what happens is that if
you detect these implicit dependencies
in the system and you visualize them
then it's very easy to see that okay if
it if I decide to take this particular
feature from a component and I pull out
that feature I try to encapsulate it
then I can see using change Captain what
else follows along when I start to pull
in this component and that is a
technique I've been using a lot over the
years to kind of make an architecture a
little bit more granular that is
actually quite quite good as well so can
really help you drive the architecture
well your efforts to change the
architecture in a way that is convenient
and not arbitrary if you like or not
Guided by simply gut Fields yeah I mean
to me the ultimate test of an
architecture is always that's the
architecture support the way we work
with the system the way we evolve the
system and what you see quite often you
actually find that teams are fighting
against their own architecture okay and
that that is quite good
and now another question so I went
through also your company page to get
some information about behavioral code
analysis
a one thing that caught my attention was
also the fact that says behavioral code
analysis can be used to measure
knowledge gaps among other things so
what kind of knowledge and what kind of
gaps are we talking about here the kind
of gaps in skills gaps in what oh this
is one of my favorite topics and
knowledge Gap it's an example of one of
those another social analysis it's about
measuring uh the code familiarity of the
current team to give you an example of
why this is important a number of years
ago I worked with a large organization
the team I worked with they were
responsible for two different code bases
and we did an analysis of the code bases
we looked for more specifically we're
looking for technical depth so we did a
hotspot analysis investigated the
hotspots did some actions plan some
ideas and towards the end of the day the
team told me that in addition to these
two code bases we actually have one more
code base so I said okay perfect let's
have a look at that one too and everyone
kind of just looked at me in a funny way
and then suddenly someone said that we
don't really have to look at it because
we know that this code base is a true
mess so I said okay that's super
interesting now we really have to look
at it so we did and it turned out that
objectively this third code base was no
worse than the other two and we actually
had spent some time comparing code
looking at code samples to convince the
team that there's no objective
difference in quality between these code
bases so why was one code base perceived
to be so much harder to understand well
it turned out that the reason was that
this code base the third code base was
of course developed a different team in
a different part of the organization
that has since been desponded and this
team simply inherited the code so the
reason that they perceived it as
complicated was because they lacked
familiarity with both the domain and the
code and this is what I mean with
knowledge and the code from Clarity
because you know Behavior code analysis
you can actually measure the familiarity
and visualize this you can show okay
where are the knowledge gaps as seen in
the code and this is important because
if you address the problem with lack of
familiarity as a technical problem and
start to refactor the code we're going
to waste a lot of time solving a problem
that possibly doesn't have to be solved
what we need to do instead is to give
the team a chance to plan their
onboarding get the proper onboarding and
become familiar with the code in their
own pace that's interesting and avoids
the conversations around the bad code is
code that I didn't write is more kind of
is more objective more than I simply
don't like that I would have written
that differently exactly exactly that's
quite common
okay so another we mentioned Legacy code
a few times here now and you often
mention behavioral code analysis of
course in the context of Legacy code and
this is I mean it's a kind of natural
thing isn't it most companies have lots
of Legacy code to deal with that still
delivers value and they have to manage
it but the first thing I would like to
ask about Legacy code is there are many
definitions about Legacy code what is
yours so my definition of legacy code is
actually very close to what you just
mentioned so definition I tend to use is
that Legacy code is coded somehow lacks
in quality and it's code that you didn't
write yourself because I do find that
these people Dimension is so much more
important that's more or less what
determines is something is Legacy code
or the next cool thing okay that is
quite interesting you know that there
was also another definition I think from
Mike feathers and others that is
basically Legacy code is called with no
tests but now in your experience have
you ever come across code that actually
is hostas is well tested but the
developers still have problems with it
and think that is actually badly written
anyway yes I have that's the main reason
why I don't use that definition myself
because and I have to share this with
you I've been analyzing so many code
bases over the years I've probably been
the last three 400 code bases of the
past decade and some of the worst
technical depth I've ever found tends to
be in the automated tests so to me
having a large test suit is absolutely
no guarantee that this system is
maintainable it could actually mean the
opposite so basically if the tests are
not written with high quality code the
tests themselves are not really going to
be very helpful to the team or at least
not helpful in terms of going faster or
understand get a better understanding of
the code base no I actually think that
if the tests themselves lacking quality
they are going to hold back your overall
efforts they are going to make the
situation worse for you so it's actually
worse than that is simply if you have
bad tests you probably are in the same
position as if they were actually there
were no tests whatsoever kind of am I
understanding correctly yeah that's
correct and I mean I've seen it all I
mean in test code we seem to I think
there are multiple reasons this happens
I think that first of all test
automation is I mean it's an old id but
it's only been mainstream for what not
like what 10 15 years or something like
that so I think that we as a community
we're still learning what good tests
look like and consequently we tend to do
things in that test automation code that
we would never ever accept in
application code and then you have the
other driver that some organizations
tend to enforce different code coverage
numbers but you worry of the do is you
simply try to meet that number right if
it makes sense or not that doesn't
really matter you try to meet it so you
see a lot of tests that don't really
test anything except that application
doesn't crash and I do think that's a
pretty low bar yeah yeah
now a bit of a small change here now we
talk about Legacy code quite a bit but
can we use behavioral code analysis also
for development of Green Green Field and
Brownfield systems yes we can I mean
Brownfield systems is so it's a perfect
use case it's really also one of the
sweet spots for Greenfield projects you
can use Behavior code analysis you need
to allow a little bit of time for
building up the behavioral data but in
my experience this goes surprisingly
quick so if you have a team with say 10
15 people then you will have enough data
in just three to four weeks to start to
do a beta code analysis because the
patterns you detect in a behavior code
analysis they're so strong so they are
there from the very beginning that's
interesting
so basically he is a kind of the path
the way teams work somehow the patterns
they interact with the code and they do
things start to appear from the very
beginning of the project and they tend
to stay stable is this am I
understanding correctly yes they do so
what you can see on many if you start to
look at the Greenfield project what you
tend to see are the parts that start to
look problematic after let's say the
first months of development very very
often if you return a year later you see
that they have just degraded further in
quality right and the earlier we can
detect these problems the more important
it is so that's one reason why I
recommend green free projects to use
Behavior code analysis on in their
day-to-day work but there's another
reason too because one thing that tends
to happen with the Greenfield projects
is that they tend to get the deadline
and I've seen so many projects that get
off to a good start very often these are
Legacy replacement projects and this
time around the organization wants to do
everything right right so you know how
messy it was to work with the Legacy
code now you're going to do the perfect
replacement system and usually starts
out well and then this time headline
happens and deadlines do tend to bring
out the worse in us and where we're very
often the whole code quality takes a
massive hit and if you don't have a
behavior code analysis in place then you
really lack that safety net right then
you lack the way of communicating inside
a team that okay this is what's going on
this is what's happening this is what we
need to focus on okay and this is quite
good because now natural follow-up
question is how can you include
behavioral code analysis within the
software development life cycle you
mentioned we are suggestion for teams to
use this in the day-to-day work okay how
can they do that I can imagine you know
integration with A continuous
integration or continuous delivery
pipelines maybe ID integration can you
give us an idea on how this should
happen yeah I like to think that there
are a couple of different use cases one
of the most important is of course to
integrate it into your CI CD or your
pull request if you're working with that
so that each time you you decide to
merge something to your main branch you
know that this is our clean merch that
you're not introducing any new problems
you're not degrading the quality of any
hot spots I think that's super important
the best way to manage technical debt is
I mean step 0 is always put the bar on
what's already there don't take on more
depth these Integrations help you with
that the other thing that I recommend is
to use Behavior code analysis as a
communication tool and what that means
is that you can use these techniques the
visualizations of code you can use them
as part of your planning meeting and
that's part of your retrospectives and
in particular I'm a big fan of using
this data in retrospectives because once
you get to retrospective you have
everything fresh in your head you know
which features you worked on you know
which parts that were painful to work on
and seeing that visualized in the
context of hotspots it's a really really
good way of driving decisions on what to
fix and what technical debt to pay down
in the next iteration so that would be
my recommendation are there any in ID
Integrations any tools to integrate
behavioral code analysis tools with the
delivery the pipelines thing basically
tools that simplify the life of
developers as far as you know what they
need to do this integration by
themselves with the existing tooling
there are tools I'm again a bit biased
because it's my startup that is doing
those tools but that's one thing we
build that codes in we build the
Integrations with code review tools and
with IDs and the idea integration is
something I'm looking forward to in
particular we are going to launch our ID
integration in during February so pretty
soon okay the next question is one a
question that I'm particularly
interested in so tools like git veteran
control systems or event tools like you
know the product project managing
systems like GD usually they assign
something to a single person but some
teams maybe not most yet they use pair
programming or ensembled also called mob
programming these techniques where
several people sometimes the entire
thing work together on a particular
feature and so the commits or the
tickets should be assigned to all of
them how does behavioral code analysis
work in this Con in that context if you
come across this this kind of
environments and what have you done to
account for this yeah that's right we
actually came across it pretty early on
because we have a couple of customers
that are using those practices of course
yes you can handle that and the way you
do it is I mean the tooling obviously
needs to know about you using a pair
programming or assemble programming and
what you do then is that as a developer
you simply need to add those extra data
fields and there are different ways you
can do that you can have like a
co-authored by tag in your commit
message or you can simply have a free
text commit message on some structured
format and if you do that then the
tooling can pick that up and it can kind
of distribute the credit and blame and
price across all members of the mobile
or the pair so it works pretty well and
I think it's practices like power
programming doesn't impact hotspots but
it impacts the knowledge metrics a lot
so you do want to take that into account
and does it impact also any any other
information because for example well
reading your books and reading the
listening also to some of your talks I
think you found out that also there are
some kind of power load distribution for
who contributes to to a project more in
terms of developers yeah so when you
have say Ensemble programming or pair
programming does this kind of
distribution change a bit does the shape
change I mean it would be super
interesting to know actually I haven't
seen seen a data set on that it would be
really interesting to see our project
that I've been doing assemble
programming from the where we start and
look at what that contribution graph
looks like I mean if we are diligent
about it and that's the only thing you
do yes then I would expect the curve to
change the reason that you tend to get
these power loss shapes is also because
on a project there are simply some
people that stay on that project for
years right so they naturally become
their main contributors I do think that
within the IT industry we had uh
historically we had a very high staff
turnover so I think it's kind of natural
that we gravitate towards those power
laws structures but I'd be really
interested to see that I haven't seen
any good data sets on the assembled
programming yet thank you and another
question this is of a different nature
so it's not a technical nature but more
ethical nature so as you mentioned I
think briefly at the beginning
also there is lots of data that comes
out of these various repositories
various tools we use for development
this data also contains a lot of
information or at least can help in
infer a lot of information about
individual Developers for example
changes they make you know working hours
possibly the effects they introduce are
there any kind of abuses we need to be
careful of if you come across any
situations where you had to somehow say
no I'm not going to do this because you
want to know information for that you
shouldn't be using in this way oh yeah
definitely a couple of years ago back in
2015 when I started code scene the way I
bootstrapped the company was by doing
services so I can kind of Finance
building up the tool back then I had so
many people asking me can you go into
our organization and can you rank all of
my programmers so I know how to to
reward and not to fire I always said no
to that and there is Jason I said no was
part ethical I simply think it's the
wrong thing to do if you need to have
that outside information as a manager
you're probably not as close to your
team as you should be and second I also
think it's genuinely where we are
unhelpful it's actually a dangerous
thing to do because the moment you start
to misuse these metrics to evaluate
individuals what you're going to do is
that everyone on that team is going to
adopt to what they are being measured
for they're going to start to game the
metrics and you're going to lose a lot
of valuable information and in the
process you're going to destroy all the
Team Dynamics so let's assume that we
take a ridiculous metric let's say that
we're measuring productivity based on
the number of commits you do as an
individual the moment you start to
measure that and evaluate that on me I'm
going to do more commits my commits will
carry more meaning but I'm going to do
more of them what's also going to happen
is that if you ask me for help I'm going
to decline to help you because I'm
basically making commits so I think it's
really really dangerous and what I did
personally was that I include that our
whole chapter in my latest books after
the sun x-rays where I learn about these
potential pitfalls and advice against
them and explain why you don't want to
do it and what we did as a company with
code scene was that we did a formal
statement that we are never going to
evaluate individuals what we do is we
could evaluate the team I think that's
fair to do because as a team you share
goals but never individuals it's simply
the wrong thing to do okay thank you now
another question instead about
behavioral code analysis and how do we
know that it works so maybe a bit of a
naughty question if you like but many
people they come up with the techniques
or tools and stuff say use these will
help you a lot we'll make your team
themes more efficient but deliver faster
better quality how do we know that
behavioral code analysis actually works
According to some objective criteria so
this question is very close to my heart
because when I wrote the first book
about behavioral co-analysis your code
is Crimson as stated already in the
forward that one thing I wanted to do
was well let me put it another way
rather what I think is an issue and that
that's what I covered in your Curtis
Crimson is that that's an industry we
have so many different opinions and then
there's the whole academic research
where we actually know what works and
what doesn't there simply isn't any good
bridge between the academic research and
the practicing programmer so that's one
thing I wanted to add with your Curtis
Crimson so a lot of these techniques
have actually been evaluated in the
academic field so you know for example
with hotspots looking at the hotspot
metric we know that that has more
predictive value than any properties of
the code itself so there is a growing
body of evidence that these techniques
actually work of course I'm trying to do
my contributions as well six months ago
me and a colleague published a paper
called code red the business impact of
code quality where we actually looked at
these metrics and see do they actually
correlate with something that means
something to the business I think it's
important because if you advise a
company and the company makes
potentially a million dollar decisions
based on your information it's simply
your responsibility as a vendor to make
sure that what you do actually works so
I hope I managed to answer the question
to some degree yeah I think you did you
answer the question very well I think
it's always a question to ask to people
that propose techniques or tools because
of course nobody proposes anything
saying use this because will not work
everybody will promote the tools but
this to me is important to understand if
there is any area any evidence behind
that and I think you answer very well
and then a different kind of question
now now we talk about Legacy code code
quality how to judge quality the impact
it has on an organization and all these
good things
but then there is an interesting entry
in your blog from 2019 why I write dirty
called code quality in context which I
read and I found quite interesting so
now can you tell us well a bit maybe
very briefly about the entry and then
how do you use behavioral code analysis
to to decide that the context yeah I'm
going to step into some Dangerous Ground
now because I know this is an unpopular
opinion the thing is that blog post was
pretty much written as a little bit of a
response to the Boy Scout rule that
always leave the code cleaner than you
found it because I simply don't think
that holds up as a general advice a very
much against this categorical
imperatives because I think context is
so important always
so the whole idea is that if we look at
code and see what's actually happening
to code as the system evolves you would
see that some parts of the code are
being changed much more frequently than
other parts this is information that you
can use to your advantage because code
quality matters in context so what that
means is that if I'm modifying a piece
of code where I know and again no is
based on measuring that this is a part
of the code where we do a lot of work
it's highly relevant to a roadmap then
yes I do want to leave that code cleaner
than I found it it's super important but
on the other hand let's say a fixed
locational bug in the long tail of
changes in the code base right so I'm in
a very stable part of the code that
haven't been touched for years when I
make modification to that part of the
code I probably don't have a good mental
model of how that code works and if I
start to refactor it there's always a
risk I'm not going to destroy something
and I might also waste time because
chances are once that bug is fixed I'm
never going to return to that code again
so that simply means that when I work in
that long tail code what I do is I
make the minimum effort I can to fix
whatever I have to fix and should I be
wrong with that bet and actually have to
return to that code again then that's
the time to refactor it so I do use this
temporary information to decide which
code do I refactor as I go along and
which code is less important that's the
ID so basically the code that does not
change a lot the change only
occasionally you don't really try to
make it much better you do the minimum
amount of work to add the functionality
or to fix a bug whatever you need to do
but you keep it to a minimum I do yeah
okay so and then if it is called that
changes very often instead you are very
careful with that bit yeah that's right
and I might actually even that's why I
use this unnecessarily provocative title
why I write through the code because I
might actually make the code worse if I
know that this is a stable part of the
code right the minimum change I can do
involves setting a couple of x-rays
statements then I do that right but I
would never do that in code that I know
is undergoing lots of heavy change okay
yeah and this is fits also in the
context so you talk about the at the
beginning we are basically using
behavioral code analysis to actually get
a if you like a good return on
investment on your time where you want
to spend time to make the code better
where you don't want instead to spend
that much time so I guess this fits all
these line of reasoning pretty well yeah
and I like to think that's important
because there is so little time and so
much code
also how a developer can make this
context decision quickly because usually
when they have to do to make changes and
do something that is some kind of time
pressure
and often people as we know developers
can go for a quick and dirty solution
but they might actually go for that in
the wrong place so how can they decide
hold on here they really need to be
careful I mean in a kind of time
constrained manner yeah so there are a
couple of things you can do what I
personally do is I always have a hotspot
analysis run on a daily basis
automatically right so I always have a
hotspot map if you look at that map a
couple of times then you start to form
that mental model you start to think of
the system in terms of hotspots that KDs
or volatile Parts these are stable parts
so that helps a lot what you can do if
you don't have that information is you
can do something very simple you can
simply do a git blame in your code
editor and you can check when was the
last time that this particular function
or part of the code was modified and if
it's more than a year back then you know
that you're looking at pretty stable
code okay that is quite a useful rule of
thumb I guess and very quick thing to do
for for developers okay and now
sometimes maybe a bit more advanced less
important so I've seen references to
machine learning and artificial
intelligence in the context of
Behavioral code analysis so what kind of
analysis and decisions do they enable
that's an interesting error it's
something I've been working with a lot
over the past years let me try to give
you one example on where I think machine
learning is generally useful and that is
something that's targeting it's a more
advanced use case and it's more
contextual because it it's a typical use
case for large organizations but let's
say that you are the tech lead or maybe
you're the software architect in a large
organization one of your
responsibilities is typically to review
code review pull requests and whatnot
and you might get tens of pull requests
today to review most of us simply cannot
pay attention to all that level of
detail throughout the whole day so after
a while you're going to slip and you're
going to miss something really really
important and of course it's also the
risk of burnout because you're going to
have this constant feeling of having to
catch up with the new request that comes
in for review
and at the same time I do think that
behavior code analysis knows to some
degree where the potential risks are so
one thing I've been working on over the
past years is to build machine learning
algorithms that can look at behavioral
data like what are the typical patterns
of modifications how do they compare to
the typical low risk modifications that
we do you can use machine learning
pretty well to predict the risk that a
particular change will introduce or
defect for example and that makes it
possible to Simply flag certain pull
requests as more risky so that you can
focus your manual expertise to where
it's likely to be needed the most okay
so will it be to some kind of tool to
help reviewers or your envisioning also
some kind of automated reviews like
somebody issues a pull request and the
system goes I run the behavioral code
analysis with the machine learning okay
everything is good I'll accept it or
there will always be a human there I
think at the moment we do want to have a
human in that Loop but that human is
going to be able to prioritize their
time in a much much better way thanks to
the machine so the way you can think
about it the way it actually looks is
that you open a pull request and the
machine says that hey this is a low risk
change you just need to do a quick
sanity check or the system can say that
this is an increased risk the cost and
then give a couple of reasons and what I
found so fascinating that when we
trained these machine learning
algorithms what we figured out was that
again it was not only properties of the
code that this term and if pull request
was likely to have a defect or not it
was actually very much up to the social
Dimension as well and to give you one
example let's say that I go in and make
a large sweeping change to the Linux
kernel that would be a gigantic risk
because I have no idea how that actually
works let's say that Linux torwalts
makes exactly the same change as I did
his risk would be much much lower
because linear lineasexual understands
the code right so there is this human
element it's obviously sensitive right
but if we really really want to fix this
audacious and the prioritize then we
need to take that social information
into account okay so the idea is is
basically to take this information into
account to somehow qualify the risk in
the change exactly so if the system
knows that is a person that is actually
knowledgeable about that part of the
system it flags as a lower risk than if
it is somebody else that is less
knowledgeable something like this yeah
that's what we saw when we looked at
what algorith actually did because I
mean a couple of risk predictions are
based on some of the vectors we used or
properties of the code properties of the
change sets but then there's the social
Dimension because the more experienced
you are in a particular area the larger
changes you can do with less risk okay
and this is still an area under
development I guess yeah so we actually
launched that feature it's available but
of course there's so much you can do
with machine learning we do try to find
a good combination because you want a
lot of things to be deterministic
because you want to be able to read some
backwards and understand okay why did we
come up with this particular decision
right so I think it's not something I
would use wisely but when you have a lot
of different data vectors with really
complicated patterns that's where I
think machine learning really shines and
this is one example on how you can use
it with behavioral code analysis data
that's quite interesting and now another
one so about the the limit of of the
techniques I mean what are the limits of
Behavioral code analysis are there any
things that you would like to achieve
but cannot be achieved or cannot be
achieved yet there is actually one thing
that's been painful to me over a couple
of years now because it's something I
would was hoping that would would have
been able to address many years ago but
I still haven't gotten a run to do it
that is change coupling that we're
talking about earlier change coupling is
super powerful in that they can reveal
this implicit dependencies that you just
cannot see in the code itself however
change happening is also bi-directional
meaning that you cannot tell in which
direction the dependency goes to me this
makes it a little bit less useful than
it actually is what I would like to do
is I would like to collect that
information and I think the only way to
collect it is by integrating into IDs
and code editors because stereo can
actually figure out that okay I modified
this file before modifying this file
gives you a direction on the change
coupling that's one obvious limitation
that I do hope to address in the near
future let's see if I'm understanding
correctly so yeah you're saying that
change coupling is at the moment is
giving us correlation data but not
causation kind of these things change
together but I don't know which one I'm
changing and then as a consequence the
other will change as well exactly and in
order to figure that out you need to
look at the code today but I do you
think that by integrating more tightly
with code editors we should be able to
figure out the direction of dependencies
okay do you think also that maybe
improvements in machine learning or
artificial intelligence can actually
help in solving this kind of issues or
that are necessary for that I'm actually
not sure I'm watching that area with a
lot of excitement because there is a lot
happening I actually think that the
advances in machine learning and with AI
I mean we have techniques like chat GPT
now and their co-pilot right and I think
what these techniques are doing I like
the direction I think it's still the
early days but I think what these
techniques are doing is that they're
making it even more important to stay on
top of your code because for a long long
time we're going to have a hybrid where
parts of the code is written by on II
and yet has to be understand by human
and if you're in that situation you do
want to make sure that you know exactly
what goes into your code and what
doesn't so that's where I think that
behavior code analysis over the decade
to come will be even more important than
at least day
now questions about getting started
let's say we have a team interested in
doing behavioral code analysis how
should they get started so say we want
to analyze our code base are there any
aspects they need to look at first you
know some kind of typical things that
you would recommend to look at first or
it depends on some context if it depends
on context what is the context so how do
they get how does a team get started
with this so if you talk about analysis
perspective I always recommend that you
start with the simplest analysis and
that's the hotspot analysis so visualize
your system understand where your
development hotspots are and make sure
that these development thoughts are
healthy that will be my starting point
because getting the hotspots under
control it's like it kind of creates the
foundation for all other things you
would like to do with that system so
that would be my recommended starting
point once you have a master debt I
think that the next good step is to
start to look at the exchange coupling
and figure out that yeah okay maybe even
if our individual models we have and if
even if they are simple enough to
understand isolation it's the system as
a whole still easy to reason about and
that's something change Kaplan can help
you with and then in addition to that
you have all these ad hoc use cases like
what if a long-term contributor leaves
the company or leaves the team where are
the knowledge gaps whether we need to
focus our onboarding efforts this
one-off analysis are a very good fit for
Behavioral code analysis too but please
start with hotspots and then change
coupling that would be my recommendation
okay thank you and also just to get
started I know that you created a free
and open source tool called codemat am I
pronouncing it correctly yes that's
right codemat okay
so with this tool what kind of analysis
can somebody perform to a code base so
with codemap you can perform the
analysis I just talked about you can run
a hotspot analysis and you can run a
change coupling analysis and you can
also do a couple of social analysis like
figuring out what does the knowledge
distribution looks like in the code base
where are the knowledge gaps you can do
those kind of things with codemap okay
and does it depend on the virtual
control system particular version
control system used by the team I don't
know is git better than subversion or
perforce or any other
Version Control Systems I mean are there
any limitations depending on the Version
Control System you use yeah there are
some limitations what I try to do with
code math is that it works with all
these Version Control Systems but
certain features are only available for
git so I try to handle that gracefully
if you request a particular the more
advanced analysis then you need to have
a git repository but you can always do a
hotspot analysis no matter what version
control system you're using okay and
these are limitations due to actually
the the data actually available in the
repositories themselves am I correct
yeah exactly I mean the main difference
is that with systems like TFS or
subversion you need to do a round trip
to the server to figure out some pretty
basic stuff like how large was this
particular change for example in terms
of lines of code you could of course
Implement that too as simply thought
that that's going to be ridiculously
expensive from a runtime perspective
right it's going to take like five hours
to run an analysis where you can
actually do it in two SEC seconds if the
data was local like it doesn't get so
that's their main reason okay as far as
you know it's these two been integrated
somehow by some teams in their own
day-to-day activities like I don't know
integrated with the continuous
integration or continuous deployment
tools maybe running scripts from command
line do you know if of any teams that
actually use code math in these ways so
I know that codemat has been extremely
popular over there so I know that lots
of teams are using it the tool itself
code map this open source tool is not a
good fit to do things like cicd
integration because it doesn't have that
concept of of analyzing a small change
set but you could still benefit from it
I mean what some teams do is simply that
they make sure to run the tool once a
day so that they always have an
up-to-date view of what their code base
looks like okay are there any other
tools that you would suggest for people
that want to try these techniques they
want just to give it a go maybe for for
a while and don't want to spend an arm
and a leg there are also any other tools
they can can use for that I mean there
are a couple of options what I did in
software the sun x-rays was that I
wanted to illustrate that you can
actually do a couple of these analysis
from the command line using your git
client if that's your kind of thing
that's definitely possible it's
obviously pretty raw information it's a
little bit limited but I still think
it's useful for this really really quick
Explorations that's one option then of
course there's a free Community Edition
for codes in if you want to benefit from
all the latest bells and whistles and
analyzes so that's also an option that
you can check out if you're interested
the Community Edition can be used for
what kind of projects it can be used for
any open source for free forever okay so
people that are working on open source
software can use that can use the
Community Edition yeah yeah is that
correct that's right okay well I think
we've done quite a good job introducing
behavioral code analysis but if there
was one thing you'd like a software
engineering to remember from this
interview what would it be if they think
about behavioral code analysis is there
one thing that is the most important
thing they should remember about it so
the most important thing to me is to
always make sure that we optimize for
understanding that's where the big big
win is an optimizing for understanding
goes beyond just the source code it's
also about making sure that the way we
work fits with what architecture
actually supports so Behavior code
analysis to me is code and people within
our business context okay and is there
anything else that we maybe missed and
you'd like to mention so I don't think
we missed anything I think we covered a
lot but they do have some news that I
could share and that is that I'm
currently working on a second edition of
your code AS Crimson I want to bring it
up to the 2023 state of the art I hope
that later this year you will be able to
check out the new edition and read much
more about behavioral code analysis okay
and also people can follow you on
Twitter is there any other way they can
get in touch if they'd like to talk to
you they're interested in behavioral
code analysis yeah definitely so you can
also connect on LinkedIn I'm Adam
Thornhill there you can Twitter probably
the best Channel but feel free to drop
me an email as well on Adam at
adamtornhill.com and I've been more than
happy to discuss these topics okay Adam
so thank you for coming on the show it's
been a real pleasure and this is
Johannes Brony for software engineering
radio thank you for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio and
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]